Calvin Tomkins Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series III: Art World Reviews and Other Writings, 1970-2006
  - The Art World: "Gloss," Recent Art Books, 1/12/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.15)
  - The Art World: "The Camel in the Tent," The Los Angeles Museum of Contemporary Art, 3/2/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.16)
  - The Art World: "Three Salons," Shows at The Whitney and Guggenheim Museums and the Third Annual International Art Exposition, 4/13/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.17)
  - The Art World: "To Watch or Not Watch," Video Art, 5/22/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.18)
  - The Art World: "$$$$," Record Art Auctions, 6/22/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.19)
  - The Art World: "The Antic Muse," Comedy in Art, 8/17/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.20)
  - The Art World: "Alfred Barr", 11/16/1981; Written on Barr's death, includes typescript notes of interview with Philip Johnson and Leo Castelli on their memories of Barr. (Box 39, Folder III.21)
  - The Art World: "An End to Chauvinism," The Geographic Spread of Contemporary Art Activity, 12/7/1981 (Box 39, Folder III.22)
  - The Art World: "Artists' Books, Art Books, and Books on Art", 1/25/1982 (Box 40, Folder III.23)
  - The Art World: "The Natural Problem," Robert Smithson, 3/29/1982 (Box 40, Folder III.24)
  - The Art World: "The Urban Capacity," Public Art, 4/5/1982 (Box 40, Folder III.25)
  - The Art World: "Seminar," Public Panel of Contemporary Artists, 6/7/1982 (Box 40, Folder III.26)
  - The Art World: "Tatyana Grossman", 8/9/1982; Includes 1 TLS (photocopy) Helen Frankenthaler-William Shawn and CT 8/13/1982 [re: clarification of dates for first editions by various artists at ULAE]. (Box 40, Folder III.27)
  - The Art World: "The Truth of Appearances," Thomas Eakins, 9/13/1982 (Box 40, Folder III.28)
  - The Art World: "Skowhegan," Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture, 9/20/1982 (Box 40, Folder III.29)
  - The Art World: "Looking for the Zeitgeist," Trends in Contemporary Art, 12/6/1982; Includes interview notes with Ivan Karp and Richard Bellamy. (Box 40, Folder III.30)
  - The Art World: "The Void," Yves Klein, 1/3/1983 (Box 40, Folder III.31)
  - The Art World: "Museums Without Walls," Recent Art Books, 1/17/1983 (Box 40, Folder III.32)
  - The Art World: "A Winner?" "The Vatican Collections: The Papacy and Art" Exhibition, 2/28/1983; Includes copy of contract between the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Governatorio dello Stato della Citta del Vaticano concerning the terms of condition for the loan and exhibition of works of art from the Vatican for the exhibition The Vatican Collections: The Papacy and Art. (Box 40, Folder III.33)
  - The Art World: "Like Water in a Glass," The Confluence of Art and Architecture, 3/21/1983 (Box 40, Folder III.34)
  - The Art World: "What the Hand Knows," Craftsmanship in Art, 5/2/1983; Photocopy of tear sheet only. (Box 40, Folder III.35)
  - The Art World: "Dallas," The Dallas Museum of Art, 6/13/1983; Includes a "collection development plan" for the Dallas Museum of Art. (Box 40, Folder III.36)
  - The Art World: "Dallas," The Dallas Museum of Art, 6/13/1983 (Box 40, Folder III.37)
  - The Art World: "Season's End," Spring Art World Activities, 7/18/1983 (Box 41, Folder III.38)
  - The Art World: "'Jazz,' Etc.," Recent Art Books, 12/19/1983; Includes handwritten interview notes from Riva Castleman regarding Matisse's Jazz. (Box 41, Folder III.39)
  - The Art World: "Alternatives," Alternative Art Spaces, 12/26/1983; Typescript interview notes with Marcia Tucker of The New Museum. (Box 41, Folder III.40)
  - The Art World: "Manet and de Kooning," Two Current Retrospectives, 2/6/84 (Box 41, Folder III.41)
  - The Art World: "Up from the I.R.T.," Graffiti Art, 3/26/1984 (Box 41, Folder III.42)
  - The Art World: "Up from the I.R.T.," Graffiti Art, 3/26/1984; Exhibition catalogs of Post-Graffiti, at the Sidney Janis Gallery in 1983, and Champions, at the Tony Shafrazzi Gallery in 1983. (Box 41, Folder III.43)
  - The Art World: "Late Picasso," "Picasso: The Last Years" Exhibition, 4/16/1984 (Box 41, Folder III.44)
  - The Art World: "Agora," MoMA Expansion, 10/15/1984 (Box 41, Folder III.45)
  - The Art World: "Talismans," "'Primitivism' in 20th Century Art" Exhibition, 10/29/1984; On the MoMA exhibition "Primitivism" in 20th Century Art: Affinity of the Tribal and the Modern[MoMA Exh. # 1382, September 19, 1984-January 15, 1985]. (Box 41, Folder III.46)
  - The Art World: "Perception at All Levels," Public Art, 12/3/1984 (Box 41, Folder III.47)
  - The Art World: "Perception at All Levels," Public Art, 12/3/1984; Includes complete galley proof of Stacy Paleologos Harris ed.,Insights/On Sites: Perspectives on Art in Public Places(Washington D.C.: Partners for Livable Places, 1984). (Box 41, Folder III.48)
  - The Art World: "Heavyweights," Recent Art Books, 2/11/1985 (Box 41, Folder III.49)
  - The Art World: "Tilted Arc", 5/20/1985; Includes a bound copy of a brief filed by Richard Serra in the U.S. Court of Appeals regarding the fate of Tilted Arc. (Box 41, Folder III.50)
  - The Art World: "Clear Painting," Donald Sultan, 6/3/1985; Includes typescript interview notes with Sultan. (Box 41, Folder III.51)
  - The Art World: "Disco," Artists and Clubs of the East Village, 7/22/1985; Includes typescript draft of article. (Box 42, Folder III.52)
  - The Art World: "The One Who Makes Pictures," Karl Bodmer, 8/26/1985 (Box 42, Folder III.53)
  - The Art World: "Knowing in Action," Abstract Art, 11/11/1985 (Box 42, Folder III.54)
  - The Art World: "Ingres in Love," Jean Auguste Ingres and The Frick Collection, 12/2/1985 (Box 42, Folder III.55)
  - The Art World: "Pleasure," Recent Art Books, 12/23/1985; Includes photocopy of typescript draft. (Box 42, Folder III.56)
  - The Art World: "Modern vs. Postmodern," Proposed Whitney Museum Expansion, 2/17/1986 (Box 42, Folder III.57)
  - The Art World: "Modern vs. Postmodern," Proposed Whitney Museum Expansion, 2/17/1986; Includes a copy of a petition against the expansion of The Whitney Museum designed by Michael Graves, with a list of all signatories, from the Ad Hoc Committee To Save The Whitney. (Box 42, Folder III.58)
  - The Art World: "Medicis, Inc.," Corporate Art Collecting, 4/14/1986 (Box 42, Folder III.59)
  - The Art World: "Medicis, Inc.," Corporate Art Collecting, 4/14/1986 (Box 42, Folder III.60)
  - The Art World: "Real and Unreal," Eric Fischl and Alex Katz, 5/12/1986 (Box 42, Folder III.61)
  - The Art World: "Out of Town," Artists in Minneapolis, 6/23/1986; Includes forty-two color slides of the artists' works. (Box 42, Folder III.62)
  - The Art World: "Passage," Jasper Johns, 8/4/1986; On the exhibition Jasper Johns: A Print Retrospective[MoMA Exh. #1423, May 19 - August 19, 1986]. (Box 42, Folder III.63)
  - The Art World: "Gods and Heroes," Plaster Casts at The Queens Museum, 9/15/1986 (Box 42, Folder III.64)
  - The Art World: "Making It New," Winslow Homer, 10/6/1986 (Box 42, Folder III.65)
  - The Art World: "Between Neo- and Post-," Neo-geo, 11/24/1986 (Box 43, Folder III.66)
  - The Art World: "Between Neo- and Post-," Neo-geo, 11/24/1986; Includes eight color slides of work by Philip Taafe and Peter Schuyff. (Box 43, Folder III.67)
  - The Art World: "Between Neo- and Post-," Neo-geo, 11/24/1986, 1988; Includes 1988 confirmation of CT's copyright to TNY articles written between 1980 and 1987, and a separate list of articles with editorial marks indicating which pieces were selected for the compilation Post- to Neo-: The Art World of the 1980's, published in 1988. (Box 43, Folder III.68)
  - The Art World: "Prodigies," Recent Art Books, 12/15/1986; Tear sheets of article only. (Box 43, Folder III.69)
  - "Brushstrokes," Roy Lichtenstein, 1987; Essay published in book, Calvin Tomkins and Bob Adelman,Roy Lichtenstein: Mural with Blue Brushstroke(New York: H.N. Abrams, 1987) Includes interview notes and summaries with Lichtenstein and other individuals, many of the summaries are from interviews conducted in the 1970s. (Box 43, Folder III.70)
  - "Brushstrokes," Roy Lichtenstein, 1987; Interview transcript with Lichtenstein. (Box 43, Folder III.71)
  - The Art World: "Peaks and Valleys," Metropolitan Museum of Art Expansion, 2/23/1987 (Box 43, Folder III.72)
  - The Art World: "Peaks and Valleys," Metropolitan Museum of Art Expansion, 2/23/1987 (Box 43, Folder III.73)
  - Department of Advance Warning: "Madonna's Anticlimax," The Book Sex, 10/26/1992; Includes typescript draft and galley proof of article. (Box 43, Folder III.74)
  - Books: "The Art Market: Going...Going...Gone,"From Manet to Manhattan: The Rise the Modern Art Market, 12/14/1992; Includes typescript draft of article. (Box 43, Folder III.75)
  - Books: "More and Less True Confessions,"Making the Mummies Dance, 2/8/1993; Includes typescript draft of article. (Box 43, Folder III.76)
  - The Art World: "St. Marcel," Marcel Duchamp, 6/21/1993; Includes typescript draft of article. (Box 43, Folder III.77)
  - Anniversary: "Merce at Seventy-Five," Merce Cunningham, 3/7/1994 (Box 43, Folder III.78)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Remembering Jackie," Jacqueline Onassis, 5/30/1994; Tear sheets only. (Box 43, Folder III.79)
  - Portfolio: "Standup Artist," Claes Oldenburg, 10/2/1995; Evidence here suggests, through an editorial mix up, that DK was asked to compose the article and only after submitting the draft was the decision made to have CT compose it instead. Includes tear sheets, typescript drafts of article by both CT and DK, interview transcript between Oldenburg and DK and interview notes. 1 TL (with autograph annotations) Franoise Mouly-Claes Oldenburg (8/31/1995)[re: invitation to contribute to TNY] 1 TLS (photocopy) Franoise Mouly-Claes Oldenburg and David Platzker (9/20/1995) [re: confirmation of terms and conditions of publication] 1 TL (facsimile) Tina Brown-DK (9/25/1995) [re: apology for editorial confusion] 1 TLS (photocopy) Claes Oldenburg-Franoise Mouly (10/8/1995) [re: compliments on article]. (Box 43, Folder III.80)
  - The Art World: "Flight Itself," Constantin Brancusi, 10/23/1995; Includes typescript draft, extensive interview transcript between CT, DK and Margit Rowell and Ann Temkin on Brancusi. (Box 43, Folder III.81)
  - The Art World: "London Calling," The Exhibition "Brilliant!", 12/11/1995; Includes typescript draft and interview transcript. (Box 44, Folder III.82)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Children of a Lesser Country," Marian Wright Edelman, 1/15/1996; Includes typescript draft and interview transcript. (Box 44, Folder III.83)
  - The Art World: "Dada and Mama," Teeny Duchamp, 1/15/1996; Typescript draft and tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.84)
  - The Art World: "Jackie's Things," Jacqueline Onassis Estate Auction, 3/11/1996; 1 TL (facsimile) Tina Brown-CT (2/26/1996) [re: revisions to article]. (Box 44, Folder III.85)
  - The Art World: "Total Abstraction," Retrospective of Abstract Art at the Guggenheim, 3/25/1996; Typescript draft and tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.86)
  - The Art World: "Picasso's True Lies," Pablo Picasso, 5/13/1996; On Picasso and Portraiture[MoMA Exh. #1743, April 24(28)-September 17, 1996] Includes typescript draft, notes, and interview transcript with William Rubin. Various facsimile letters and drafts from Andrew Wylie to William Rubin outlining the possible joint sale as a movie property of Living Well... and Rubin's article "The Pipes of Pan: Picasso's Aborted Love Song to Sara Murphy,"ARTNews 93, (5) (May): 138-147.. (Box 44, Folder III.87)
  - The Art World: "The Time of His Life," Keith Haring, 7/8/1996 (Box 44, Folder III.88)
  - Showcase: "Merce's Ocean," Merce Cunningham, 7/15/1996; Typescript draft and tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.89)
  - The Art World: "Found Generation," Gerald Murphy, 7/22/1996; Includes 1 AL (photocopy) Gerald Murphy-CT (n.d.) [re: reflections on modern art] Typescript draft of article. (Box 44, Folder III.90)
  - Caption: "Ray in Love," Man Ray, 9/30/1996; Tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.91)
  - At the Galleries: "The Good China," Roy Lichtenstein, 9/30/1996; Includes typescript draft of article and interview transcripts. (Box 44, Folder III.92)
  - The Art World: "On the Edge," Yayoi Kusama, 10/7/1996 (Box 44, Folder III.93)
  - Caption: "Artaud Head On," Antonin Artaud, 10/7/1996; On Antonin Artaud: Works on Paper[MoMA Exh. #1753, October 1(3), 1996-January 7, 1997] Tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.94)
  - Caption: "Cabaret Arensberg," Dada in New York City, 11/11/1996; Tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.95)
  - The Art World: "The Changing Picture," Jasper Johns, 11/11/1996; On Jasper Johns: A Retrospective[MoMA Exh. #1754, October 15(20), 1996-January 21, 1997] Tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.96)
  - At the Galleries: "Different Strokes," Gerhard Richter, 11/25/1996 (Box 44, Folder III.97)
  - The Art World: "Duchamp and New York," Marcel Duchamp, 11/25/1996; Includes two typescript drafts. (Box 44, Folder III.98)
  - Showcase: "Le Closeup," Francois-Marie Ranier, 12/2/1996 (Box 44, Folder III.99)
  - Caption: "Top Hat and Tail," Sir Edwin Landseer, 1/13/1997; Tear sheets only. (Box 44, Folder III.100)
  - At the Museums: "Kiss and Tell," Edvard Munch, 1/20/1997 (Box 44, Folder III.101)
  - The Art World: "De Kooning as Melodrama," Willem de Kooning, 2/10/1997; On Willem de Kooning: The Late Paintings, The 1980s[MoMA Exh. #1759, January 22(23)-April 29, 1997]. (Box 44, Folder III.102)
  - Artist's Easel" "Paint it Black," Robert Colescott, 5/19/1997; Includes typescript draft and twelve color slides of Colescott's work. (Box 44, Folder III.103)
  - The Art World: "A Question of Human Presence," Still Lifes, 6/9/1997; On Objects of Desire: The Modern Still Life[MoMA Exh. #1772, May 21(25)-August 26, 1997] Includes typescript draft of separate article on the show by DK including reflections by numerous prominent artists and interview notes with them Also includes eight color slides of artwork. (Box 44, Folder III.104)
  - The Art World: "Love for Sale," Estate Auction of the Duke and Duchess of Windsor, 8/11/1997 (Box 45, Folder III.105)
  - At the Museums: "Urbane Decadent," Christian Schad, 9/29/1997 (Box 45, Folder III.106)
  - The Art World: "Master of Invention," Robert Rauschenberg, 10/13/1997; Includes complete checklist of the Rauschenberg retrospective at the Whitney. (Box 45, Folder III.107)
  - At the Galleries: "Finely Tooned," Christian Schumann, 10/20/1997 (Box 45, Folder III.108)
  - The Art World: "Accidental Affair," Victor and Sally Ganz, 11/10/1997; Multiple typescript drafts, extensive interview transcript between DK and Sally Ganz, and program to the memorial service for Ganz held at MoMA at which CT spoke. (Box 45, Folder III.109)
  - Caption: "Haute Cartoon," Isaac Mizrahi, 11/10/1997 (Box 45, Folder III.110)
  - The Art World: "The Fame Factory," Andy Warhol, 12/1/1997 (Box 45, Folder III.111)
  - At the Museums: "Sunbaked Klee," Paul Klee, 12/8/1997 (Box 45, Folder III.112)
  - At the Galleries: "Moving Pictures," David Hockney, 1/12/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.113)
  - At the Museums: "Broken Window," Robert Delaunay, 2/2/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.114)
  - Caption: "High Styles," George Condo, 2/9/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.115)
  - The Talk of the Town: "The Creative Life," Richard Bellamy, 7/6/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.116)
  - The Art World: "Mind Games," Charles Ray and Andrew Wyeth, 7/20/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.117)
  - Artist's Easel: "Russian Blue," Alexei von Jawlensky, 7/27/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.118)
  - At the Museums: "Late Light," Claude Monet, 9/7/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.119)
  - Art: "East to West," Asian Art, 9/14/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.120)
  - The Art World: "The Escape Artist," Mark Rothko, 9/29/1998; Includes 1 TLS Ben Heller-CT (9/28/1998) [re: clarification of Rothko's use of the term "mishegas"]. (Box 45, Folder III.121)
  - Caption: "Hall of Studies," "Master Drawings from the Hermitage and Pushkin Museums", 10/12/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.122)
  - Showcase: "Nature Poet," Susan Hartnett, 11/9/1998 (Box 45, Folder III.123)
  - Caption: "Art in the Family," Kiki Smith and Family, 1/25/1999 (Box 45, Folder III.124)
  - The Talk of the Town: "At the Museums," The Merger Between P.S.1 and MoMA, 2/15/1999 (Box 45, Folder III.125)
  - Artist's Easel: "Object Lessons," Donald Sultan, 4/5/1999 (Box 45, Folder III.126)
  - The Art World: "Out of the Attic," New Greek Galleries at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 4/19/1999; Includes interview notes with Phillippe de Montebello and Carlos Picon and packet of six color slides of Greek artwork. (Box 45, Folder III.127)
  - The Art World: "New Orleans Interlude," Edgar Degas, 5/31/1999 (Box 45, Folder III.128)
  - Onward and Upward with the Arts: "Measuring Up to Nature," David Smith, 7/19/1999 (Box 45, Folder III.129)
  - At the Museums: "Dynamo,", Unpublished (Box 45, Folder III.130)
  - Postscript: "The Lion," Leo Castelli, 9/6/1999; Includes photocopies of profiles on Castelli and Ileana Sonnabend (see Series II.A) and typescript draft of Profile on Sonnabend as well as articles and material on Castelli from the 1960s and 1970s. (Box 46, Folder III.131)
  - Postscript: "The Lion," Leo Castelli, 9/6/1998 (Box 46, Folder III.132)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Table Talk," Julia Child, 11/8/1999 (Box 46, Folder III.133)
  - Postscript: "Balancing Act," Alexander Liberman, 12/6/1999 (Box 46, Folder III.134)
  - Takes: [Excerpt from Profile: "Living Well is the Best Revenge" (7/28/1962)], 4/10/2000 (Box 46, Folder III.135)
  - Essay on Robert Rauschenberg, 5/19/2000; Short essay written for a symposium in honor of Rauschenberg's acceptance of the 8th Wexner Prize at the Wexner center for the Arts, the Ohio State University. (Box 46, Folder III.136)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Looking Up: Birds of America Make a Manhattan Pit Stop," David Allen Sibley, 6/12/2000 (Box 46, Folder III.137)
  - The Talk of the Town: "At the Museums: How New York Got Full of Itself," "Art and the Empire City: New York, 1825-1861" Exhibition, 10/2/2000 (Box 46, Folder III.138)
  - "Bear Island," R. Buckminster Fuller, 2001; Written for and published in the book Thomas T.K. Zung ed.,Buckminster Fuller: Anthology for the New Millennium(New York: St. Martin's Press, 2001). (Box 46, Folder III.139)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Horizon Dept.: Towers of Light," The World Trade Center Memorial Installation, 10/1/2001; Includes glossy reproductions of Towers of Light concept renderings. (Box 46, Folder III.140)
  - The Talk of the Town: "The Creative Life: A Troupe Turns Fifty," Merce Cunningham, 7/8/2002 (Box 46, Folder III.141)
  - Portfolio: "After the Towers," Artists Concepts for World Trade Center Memorials, 7/15/2002 (Box 46, Folder III.142)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Collaboration Tempted," Robert Wilson, 8/19/2006 (Box 46, Folder III.143)
  - "An Object in Nature," Robert Rauschenberg, May 2003; A brief essay on the combine,Minutiae, by Robert Rauschenberg, written for a Sotheby's sales catalogue when the work was up for auction. Includes photograph of work. (Box 46, Folder III.144)
  - The Talk of the Town: "At the Museums: First Cities," "Art of the First Cities" Exhibition, 5/5/2003 (Box 46, Folder III.145)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Light Show: Rockets' Red Glare," Cai Guo-Qiang, 9/15/2003 (Box 46, Folder III.146)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Checking In: Clean Gene," Eugene McCarthy, 1/19/2004 (Box 46, Folder III.147)
  - The Talk of the Town: "At the Museums: A Picasso Facelift,"Les Demoiselles d'Avignon, 5/24/2004 (Box 46, Folder III.148)
  - The Talk of the Town: "At the Galleries: Unzipped," Timothy Greenfield Sanders, 11/22/2004 (Box 46, Folder III.149)
  - Briefly Noted:Art and the Power of Placement by Victoria Newhouse, 5/23/2005 (Box 46, Folder III.150)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Dynasties: Modern at Ninety," MoMA and David Rockefeller, 5/30/2005; Includes interview notes with David Rockefeller, Glenn Lowry. (Box 46, Folder III.151)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Dept. of Precocity: Artists in Their Youth," Group Show of Art Students, 2/27/2006 (Box 46, Folder III.152)
  - The Talk of the Town: "The Creative Life: The Pour," Barnaby Furnas, 3/13/2006 (Box 46, Folder III.153)
  - The Talk of the Town: "Studio Visit: The Queen, Continued," George Condo, 10/23/2006 (Box 46, Folder III.154)
  - Caption: Unpublished Caption About Art Posters, ca. 12/11/2006 (Box 46, Folder III.155)
  - Unpublished Article on Renzo Piano and Expansion of the Whitney, [Original folder title: "The Building - Renzo"] News clippings leaflets. (Box 46, Folder III.156)
- Series IV: Books, 1968-1998
  This series comprises material gathered and created for the various original books Tomkins published throughout his career. Many of the books began their life as articles in The New Yorker or drew heavily on research conducted in the course of that writing. Specific descriptions of materials for each book follow below.
  - Subseries IV.A:Eric Hoffer: an American Odyssey
    Eric Hoffer: an American Odyssey(New York: Dutton, 1968) was an expansion of the Profile Tomkins wrote for The New Yorker published in January, 1967. The one file in this subseries was found among the files for the article and moved here. But other materials concerning this book can be found elsewhere in the collection. The book contract can be found in folder I.5 among Tomkins' correspondence and materials from the original article can be found in folders II.A.20, II.A.21 and II.B.7. Correspondence with Hoffer, most regarding the article and following book, can be found in numerous folders of Series I.
    - Eric Hoffer, n.d.; [Original folder title: "Book Shop"] Photocopy of "master manuscript," typescript of book with numerous hand edits and an introduction by Eric Sevareid. (Box 47, Folder IV.A.1)
  - Subseries IV.B:Merchants and Masterpieces, 1860-1989
    Tomkins was contacted by The Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1968 to write the history of the institution coincident with their centennial celebrations, and Merchants and Masterpieces: The Story of the Metropolitan Museum of Art(New York: Dutton) appeared in 1970. The first twenty-four folders in this subseries are in order of the book chapters to which they pertain and concern succeeding eras of the museum's history and key trustees, directors and curators. Materials include copious photocopies of museum documents such as letters and manuscript material from the museum archives as well as copies of museum bulletin articles, book chapters and other published material. Large quantities of handwritten and typewritten notes are present as well. Folders 25-33 contain correspondence concerning the book, financial summaries of gifts and acquisitions by the museum, and the contents of a series of binders dedicated, respectively, to trustees and benefactors, curatorial departments, and presidents, directors, and staff of the museum. Two additional folders contain photographs used in the book and pamphlets and gallery guides from across the museum's history. Folders 34-47 are research materials and resources gathered after original publication, in many cases used for additions included in the 1989 reprint by Henry Holt. In these last files there is a particular focus on the "scandals" of the museum in the 1970s and Thomas Hoving's tenure as director
    For correspondence regarding initial discussions and the eventual contract for the book see folders I.4-I.6
    - Reports of the President, 1970-1977; Photocopies of published annual reports of the president and director of the museum. (Box 47, Folder IV.B.1)
    - Reports of the President, 1977-1986; Photocopies of published annual reports of the president and director of the museum. (Box 47, Folder IV.B.2)
    - Museum-U.S., News clippings, unpublished manuscripts, articles, and notes on the founding of various museums and collections. (Box 47, Folder IV.B.3)